<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Mads Ravn</title>
 <link href="http://madsravn.dk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://madsravn.dk/"/>
 <updated>2012-11-25T00:05:01+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://madsravn.dk</id>
 <author>
   <name>Mads Ravn</name>
 </author>
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>First post with Jekyll</title>
   <link href="http://madsravn.dk/posts/first-post"/>
   <updated>2012-10-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://madsravn.dk/posts/first-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First post with jekyll:&lt;/b&gt; This is my first post with the jekyll engine. While I have yet to understand all the wonders of it, I find it most awesome.
You can find more information about the jekyll engine on Github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am also using &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax&quot;&gt;this short overview&lt;/a&gt; to learn the markdown syntax used by Github to render the pages on github pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been following &lt;a href=&quot;http://zachholman.com/&quot;&gt;Zach Holmans blog&lt;/a&gt; for some time now and I eagerly been reading about his work at Github and what he feels is a hot topic on a given blog-post date. I came to admire him: Writing exciting stuff, working at github and having friendly and funny discussion on Twitter and at Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then did what others do when they strive to achieve: I imitated the person having what I wanted to have. I have borrowed the idea of using Jekyll on Github and the design of the blog from Zach &amp;ndash; with permission of course. I have it a bit, though &amp;ndash; my name instead of his name, some small details as sizes in the style and then &lt;a href=&quot;http://evafrederiksen.blogspot.dk/&quot;&gt;my girlfriend&lt;/a&gt; made some new icons for my menu since the ones Zach had weren&amp;rsquo;t free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My idea is to change the look and feel of the site gradually over time since design isn&amp;rsquo;t really my strong suit and right now I&amp;rsquo;m quite content with the look. But I can imagine that eventually I want a site which I have made mostly entirely myself instead of a site where only 10% of the design is my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do I want to do with this site? I want to showcase my current projects, write about solutions to problems I encounter at school or at work, tell people about my interest and what I think could be a hot topic. I am recent convert to vim and I have also recently begun playing a great deal of chess, so I could imagine I am going to write some posts about that since I would both like to share my thoughts on those topic and get some input on my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
